OK, Larry.
We're back.
And we'll start
again now I should
say with your
experiences in Dachau.
Yeah, OK.
Dachau it was already
a more famous camp.
It was--
It was a what camp?
Famous.
Oh, famous.
I didn't understand.
More famous camp.
It was kept more and orderly.
There used to come international
visits from the Red Cross
and from so.
So therefore, it was one
of the top-notch camps.
And it was kept.
How lucky you were there, right?
You ain't kidding.
That was compared with what's
been going on in other places,
we were real lucky.
Can you imagine?
So, but the luck
didn't last that long.
We stayed there for
three days, four days.
And then we were shipped from
there about a half a day's ride
in a car, in a train near
Landsberg called Lager Seven.
Near Landsberg.
Landsberg is in what country?
In Germany.
That was in Germany,
not far from Dachau.
This was another work camp
you were being sent to.
Work camp, another lager, yes.
The same people that
you were with Warsaw.
In the Warsaw ghetto.
And who had made
the march with you?
Whoever was left.
Yes, the same group that was
left from the Warsaw ghetto
from there.
The 2,000 of you or whatever.
Right.
And the first one who were
there before I arrived,
and the ones who came with me.
Whatever-- they needed a
certain number of workers?
Yes, right.
OK.
So we came back.
They took us.
We arrived in Landsberg.
Landsberg was in the ground,
so to speak, was underground.
It was built like the
Eskimos built their houses
from ice, the same way.
Igloos.
Yes, the same way was
built, but made with--
Earth.
Earth and the top and
green grass on it.
And we lived inside.
Inside there was plain wood and
straw, and you had a blanket,
and that's it.
Landsberg was how far
from what big city?
Do you know, have any idea?
Landsberg in itself
is a big center point.
It's a big city in Germany.
Today it's still in existence?
It still is, right.
I see.
That's number one.
And Landsberg, Hitler himself
was locked in, in that jail.
I see.
Not far from the Landsberg jail.
So I had the privilege of being
close to Hitler's own history.
OK.
Being there for about five or
six weeks, typhus broke out.
So they quarantined
the whole camp.
Nobody could go in and
nobody could go out.
Do you have any idea how many
thousands were in this lager?
It's in the thousands.
I have no-- I have no
idea of the exact figure.
You mean nobody could go
out of his little hut?
No, out of our huts,
you could go out.
To work.
The camp, you couldn't--
Couldn't leave to go to work.
No.
It was sealed off
completely with them,
that whoever will
survive will survive.
Whoever will die will die.
But after three days, they
decided to take a gamble.
And whoever was
still in good shape,
they took him out
and see maybe they
can use him somewhere to work.
So I still was good shape.
They took me out from
there and took me
to a camp not far from there.
We walked, about three
hours walk called Kaufering,
lager vier.
That's called means the
same camp like there was
Landsberg, number seven.
Not far from there was a little
village called Kaufering.
And that was called
number camp number seven.
OK.
But it still belonged
to the same area.
I see.
So, and from there, we went to
work to the baustelle Holzmann.
Holzmann is a
German organization.
A baustelle, it's a
construction company
that exists till this day.
I see.
So what kind of
work were you doing?
So we went to work there.
We worked there at night.
For construction, building
underground airports, and stuff
like that, construction work.
OK.
The food was lousy, and we
deteriorated it all of us.
And there one day, my father
couldn't go to work anymore.
My uncle, and all of that.
This particular older generation
couldn't take it anymore.
And they started to deteriorate.
Did you have any
idea about how old
your father was at that time?
At the time, 48.
But like an old man.
Completely broken,
completely old.
And he started to
deteriorate, and deteriorate,
water in their knees,
water in their feet.
And one day, they came
in and took him away.
And that--
That was the last
saw your father?
One morning, I just said,
I'll see you tonight
when I come back.
I left him in the camp.
I went to work.
I came back home, and he was
gone, not only him all of them,
never to be seen,
never to be heard.
And I don't know how he
died or where he died,
and what he died.
But I assumed that he was taken
from there close to Dachau.
And he was thrown in and
he died somewhere in Dachau
in the gas chamber or
something like that.
Were you-- now we
are in lager seven.
I mean lager four.
The Americans are approaching.
That the--
You've heard rumors.
Rumors, we already know that
D-day took place a long time
ago.
And this was already then.
That's already '44, close to--
this is already not '44,
this is already '45.
That's already early spring,
late, late winter of '45.
OK.
Right.
We cannot go anymore to work.
I had typhus.
The camp was closed off,
no medication, no medicine.
I have typhus.
But I remember
the doctor telling
me, if you get
ever get sick there
is one thing what you
should do, try not
to make dirt under yourself.
Stay clean as much as you can.
God knows I crawled on my feet.
I did everything.
And the only thing I
will forever never forget
is I tried to crawl out
of my block, get out,
and I crawled to the gate.
And I wanted to get
out of the gate.
And on the other
side of the gate,
there was a German,
two German guards, SS.
And one had his rifle
like this to my head.
And he says to
me, push the door.
If I push the door he
should be able to kill me.
So the other guard came
over to him and said,
[GERMAN], leave him alone.
He says, exhaustion, fatigue.
He's already finished anyhow.
Save yourself.
He was a little bit more--
a little bit more humane.
Yeah, he says, leave him.
He is dead anyhow.
So save yourself the bullet.
Just leave him alone.
So and I broke down there,
and I fall down there.
I don't know for how
long I remained there.
But I mean remained
there and I lined up
being back in my barrack, to be
shortly I made it in 28 days.
I had no food, no nothing, I
survived without medication,
or without everything.
I'm here, thank God.
What do you get with this?
What do you mean 28 days?
Until--
28 days I was out of
food, out of water.
Oh, I see.
Out of medication.
OK.
With being the way
I was, high fever.
Then actually you were
liberated at that point?
Then one morning we
woke up, and they
said they are going
to evacuate us again.
We had to go out
of the barracks.
We got out of the barracks.
As sick as you were?
As sick as we were, we
just schlepped on our feet,
and all that.
We have been sitting
there outside and waiting.
Finally, we helped each
other to crawl in the trains.
And they were, again,
taking us God knows where.
I don't know where
they were taking us
from one place to the other.
The Air Force came in,
the American Air Force.
They shot the locomotive out.
So the train couldn't move.
And we were stuck on the track.
And as we were
stuck on the track,
and they started
to bomb the track,
I only remember that
somehow I jumped over
from the inside out.
It was like a coal,
they're transporting
coal, and that kind of--
It was open.
It was open on the top.
On the top.
I see.
Yes.
That kind of--
So you were able to jump over.
Right, I jumped over, and I fall
down, and I opened up the door.
And we opened it up so the
inside started to escape.
And the ones that started
to run away, all of a sudden
started to be shot at.
We didn't know from where
then I looked around,
and I realized what happened
we came in a two way lane.
And next to us stopped
an army train loaded
with soldiers and
with flags, with fire,
you know anti-aircraft
fire and all of.
That.
And they thought that if--
The German army?
Yes, the trains will come and
see that we are who we are,
they we will not
bomb them, and then
they will be able to
retaliate and shoot.
So they used us as an escape.
Almost like a hostage.
A hostage, right.
But as soon I realized
what happened,
and I told some of
my boys, I still
had original from we started
out eight from my hardcore,
you remember in the beginning.
Right, but they were--
There were three left.
Only three.
Together three.
Myself, and two more.
There were three left.
The other ones got killed,
died, and that's it.
Typhus took some of them.
And were only three left.
We got together.
I don't want to go in again
on something on that because.
It will sound like
I'm always the hero
and always something can
happen, and I'm always doing
something for somebody else.
A girl gets shot.
OK, so the three
of you were left.
And did you--
And some of them got away.
You got away, the three
of you and others.
We got away, we run
away in the forest.
We run away.
There was a little
forest we got in.
And it poured and
rained outside.
And we stayed there.
We found some ammunition
guns that the German ,
army the soldiers threw away
from themselves, and you know.
And finally the next
day in the morning
we went in a little small
village called Schwabhausen,
and there we seen
the American army.
We were liberated.
As soon as we saw the Americans,
the first thing the said to us,
sit down and stay here.
You were still in
this prison clothing.
Prison clothing, all that, all
walking like-- they recognized
it right away who we are.
OK.
Well you had to be terrible.
Oh, yeah.
Well I weighed--
what did I weigh?
38 kilos.
What does it mean
38, kilos is what?
About two kilos to
a pound I think,
Yeah so about 20 pounds or 25
pounds, complete skin and bone.
I just crawled you could
see everything on me.
Just like you see it in
the picture, when you see.
That's exactly the way I looked.
Did you think that
you would survive?
No, I didn't believe it.
What gave you strength and hope?
Well, the strength,
like I said, you
remember in the beginning
I said that kept me.
And I said, nothing is going
nothing's going to break me.
I'm going to survive no
matter what under any kind
of circumstances.
And they got me
into the hospital.
Wonderful, wonderful.
And at the hospital--
Hospital there, an American
Hospital in Germany?
Yes, an army hospital.
They took us in.
The first thing they
cleaned us, of course,
and they checked us out.
And the first, the
second meal is a story
to be seen, or be
told in itself.
And in the way by knowing
that the food is here,
and even knowing the
food will be served,
and when the nurses came
in and served the bed here
for the guy, that the
guy on the end of the bed
jumped out and ran over
here, and grabbed the food.
Afraid that he
wouldn't get his share.
A raid, like a raid.
This is when I broke down.
This is when I cried.
And I had a 50, the only--
well, 50 years take or
give a little bit older,
the only older guy who
survived with us at this point,
he was six years in the camps.
And he survived.
And he was the
only one till then.
This was all--
And we both-- this is
already after the break.
1945.
That's in 1945.
This is when?
May, in May.
May, all right.
And you're in the hospital.
Yes that's May whatever.
Yeah that's in May,
right in month of May.
We are in the hospital.
We are liberated.
And how old at this time, you're
almost-- you're 20 years old.
I'm already now 20 years old.
Right, OK.
Yeah, it's one month before--
And you've lived a lifetime.
Right?
That's one month before
my 20th birthday.
I was born in June.
June is my birthday, so was one
month before my 20th birthday.
And he is crying and I'm crying.
We are happy, but
yet what he says,
look what he made out of us.
The food is here already.
We are liberated.
We are still like animals.
And I woke up the next
morning sleeping next to him.
I want to call him, and I see
his laying with his hand down.
So I thought maybe he feels.
The man died.
He had a heart attack.
The doctor told me.
How old was this man?
Your age, young man.
He was in his close to 50.
Oh, I see.
He was the only older guy.
I'm young for my age.
The doctor told me he
died of a heart attack
because he says the concept
of being free after six years.
Yes.
That's--
Just couldn't take it.
Couldn't take it, and he died.
OK, then you're liberated.
Now, where did you go?
How long did you
stay in the hospital?
How long did it take
you to recuperate?
I stayed in the hospital
for about a month's time.
In June, they transported
us back to Czechoslovakia.
They asked who wants to go back.
Of course, the war is over.
Czechoslovakia is
Czechoslovakia.
I went back to Czechoslovakia.
You went home to look--
try to find family.
I'm not home yet.
I'm in-- I'm in Prague.
And in Prague I met girls
who came from Germany,
from my hometown, and they
told me that my sister is alive
and she is in Bergen-Belsen
in the British zone,
the British occupation.
And she is there.
She's been liberated.
Right, and she is there
and that she is alive.
So now, I know my
sister is alive.
This is one sister of four.
Four, and the rest of
them I didn't even count.
I haven't counted on her
either, but somehow she managed.
Because she was
already 14 years old.
And the other ones were younger?
One younger.
Were you the oldest
in your family, Larry?
I was the oldest in the family.
I see.
OK.
I'm in Czechoslovakia.
I meet with my boys.
I found from the two
boys who survived
with me, we are three from
our original gang of 16,
four more is available.
And one more we found
later on another one.
We are becoming again
a group of eight.
Half of us survived.
We decide we are going
to go home and take
a look what's going on at home.
So of us say they
don't want to go.
I decided I'm going to go
just for one more time.
I went.
I wish I would be
a poet or a writer
to describe the
feelings, and how it was,
and what it just went through,
village after village,
small town after
small town, empty.
No Jewish life, no death.
No houses destroyed, empty.
You know, like
nature takes his tool
on emptiness, and all of that
grass growing everywhere,
no nothing.
It's '45 fall.
I leave home.
I'm on my way to Budapest.
Now, you will be
able to understand
on the beginning what
I wasn't able to say,
because it didn't work out
as now you will understand.
OK.
Here--
So you went to Budapest.
It's '45.
In Budapest I meet
with Joel Brand.
This is the same Joel Brand
that dealt with Eichmann before.
I saw Eichmann in 1943.
But I didn't know who
he is at the time.
Where did you see him?
In Budapest.
Oh before the-- this was before?
Before the arrest, right?
To me, we saw.
I didn't know his name.
I saw an SS man, but an
officer, a German SS officer.
I didn't know who he is.
I didn't know what it meant.
Eichmann didn't mean
nothing to me at the time.
Sure.
Now it meant everything already.
We knew already, and Joel Brand.
You mean in 1945
you knew already?
Oh, yes.
Sure.
We had a long talk
with Joel Brand.
And Joel Brand told me
then, and he says someday we
will be in Israel.
Israel will be liberated.
And we'll be able to talk.
Right now, our main
objective is to get,
to create the state of Israel.
OK.
So this is from Budapest.
Then where did you go?
In Budapest, there were
transports leaving for Italy
and back to Germany.
I decided my first priority is
to go back and see my sister.
She doesn't know that I'm
alive but I do know about her
So you're going to I
wrote a letter here
to America to my uncle from
Germany from the hospital.
There was a doctor,
a Jewish doctor
who was in the army
who came to visit.
I don't this.
This is I'm finding out later.
He says, he asked if anybody
has family in America.
And I said yes, I have an
uncle by the name of Janowitz,
and he lives in Cleveland, Ohio.
That's all I know.
So he took the name.
He took the address.
He came back to the States.
He looked up at the telephone.
He found my uncle, the
address, he called him up.
Later, years later,
my uncle tells me
he gets a call on
a Saturday night.
The man on the other line
introduces himself as Rabbi
so and so.
And he says, I have
a message for you
by the name of Leibi Hersch.
And he is your
sister's son, Leah.
The son.
That he is a survivor.
He is the only thing that
he knows he is alive.
He is going to go
home to look around.
He doesn't know who
survived or who didn't.
But my sister already did the
same thing with somebody else.
And he already knew.
He already was in
correspondence with my sister.
But I don't know all of that.
OK.
Now I'm leaving Budapest.
I'm on my way to Prague.
In Prague, I meet
one of my friends.
How do you get to
these different places?
Just by train.
Jump on a train and go.
Oh, were there trains
were running at that time?
Running trains,
yeah loaded to top.
Everybody's running around.
Yeah, OK.
I jump on a train take Budapest.
I ate breakfast here,
supper I already
had in a different
country, if I had supper.
But I had a piece of bread
what you could put together.
Yeah.
In Prague, I meet one of the
boys who went in '42 and in '43
for Aliyah to Palestine.
He is with the
Jewish Bricha back.
He came back.
He says, Larry,
big hug, you know.
I got a job for you.
For me?
Come with me.
He took me away.
I became a member of the
Irgun right there and then.
That was the top.
And I started to work
for the Irgun from there.
There or you went to Israel?
With the Bricha.
First, my job was,
because the fact
that I spoke all
those languages,
is I used to bring transport
let's say to smuggle them out
between the Hungarian
border to Austria,
from the Polish
from Czechoslovakia to
Austria, or to Germany,
all dependent on what it was.
So how many years
did you do that?
I worked in that
from '45 till '47.
Two years.
In the beginning of '47
I left for Palestine.
I became active.
How did you make that trip?
On what you called
Aliyah Bet, which
is called Aliyah Bet
is the secret, the--
Well, I know.
But did you travel by train?
Did you travel by ship?
No, no, no, by ship.
By ship.
You went in the Mediterranean.
Mediterranean, from Italy, yes.
So you had to go down.
Oh, you were in
Italy at that time.
OK, fine.
From Italy, and from Italy
we went to on a little boat.
So how long did that take?
It take me 10 days.
That's all.
Yes.
I was in Israel, in Palestine.
I was active in different
things with the Irgun.
And with eight months
later, rumors already
that the state of
Israel will be created.
It's just a matter of time.
The United Nations voted for
it, and all of that activity
going on.
So it was already a fact
that the state of Israel,
just a matter of time.
But in the meantime, somehow the
British got hold of my picture
in Germany.
And they knew who I was.
So the decision was made instead
of them to get hold of me,
they have been looking for me.
I had to leave once
more Palestine.
So I was smuggled out on a boat.
I had to walk in.
I was put in a--
between oranges and grapefruit.
Yes.
And put in a hole.
To go where?
And I went, the best
way for me was not
to go anywhere else, just
to go direct to the British.
So I went from
Palestine to Cyprus.
All right.
And let me just interrupt
you for a minute.
Direct to the British
in their own mouth.
You went back.
You told me that you actually
before you got involved
in this, you went back.
It was your choice
to go back to Germany
to look for your sister.
I went back to Germany.
Did you find her?
Oh, yes.
I found my sister.
And then you said goodbye.
I'm going to go.
I said to my sister, yeah, I
had things to do, as long as I--
she knew that I'm alive,
and she knew that I'm alive.
OK.
And--
She was probably in a displaced
persons camp or something
at the time.
Yes, she was in a DP camp.
And she left to America in 1947.
I see.
She came to America.
You had no more contact
with her at that point.
Just writing, but when
I was in Palestine.
I didn't write her
anything, we didn't.
No contact at all.
My uncle once in a while
he used to drop a letter.
But I didn't want them
to send me anything.
Because for give away.
Right, subversive.
Right.
Then I was smuggled out.
I went to Cyprus on a boat.
And from the same boat, I went
back all the way to France.
And from France, I was
taken back to Germany.
So I left in 1947.
Sometimes it would be by the
end of May, I left in '47.
By February of '48, I
was back in Germany.
OK, now let's just skip
over some of these years.
And tell us when you
came to this country.
When did you come to America--
I came to America in '56.
--or to the US or to Cleveland?
Cleveland, I came in 1956.
After that eight year period
then, what did you do?
You were working for
the Irgun all this time?
No, no, no.
The Irgun dissolved in 1948
after the establishment
of the State of Israel.
When I was in Germany and in
'48, at the beginning of '48,
I was active with the Irgun
doing different things
at different places.
In '48, I received the
standard order to report back,
coming back to
Israel, which if you
remember the story
with the boat Altalena.
That boat came and was in
confrontation with Ben-Gurion,
and with the army at the time.
So I came back on the
Altalena, and after there, we
were ending to the army.
I joined the army.
You were in the Israeli army.
The Israeli army,
and stayed there.
I stayed in the Israeli army for
eight years, till the 1956 war.
Oh, the Six-Day War.
In '56.
Was that the Six-Day War?
No, no, '67 was the Six-Day
War. '56 was another thing.
All right.
Excuse me.
After the '56 war,
I came to America.
OK.
In America--
How did you come here?
I came to my sister
who was here already.
She was married.
Did she-- did you need help
to come here at that time?
Oh, yes, well but no, no
organization or anything
of this nature, no help.
It came from my own
family, from my--
I see.
No--
No religious organization--
No religious organization.
--welcomed you or anything.
Because you had
family here already.
Yes.
OK, it was your sister.
She was here already
too by my uncle.
She came to my uncle.
My uncle took her out and all.
He paid for her.
This was this Mr. Janowitz
who lived in Cleveland.
Yes.
And he saw that she got here.
Right.
He took her our.
I see.
And she stayed in their house.
And they just took her in
one of their own daughters.
So you came here in '56.
At that time, so you were
not married then, you said.
No, at that time
I wasn't married.
I married.
I met my wife here in Cleveland.
Did you live with your uncle
and your sister when you came?
Yes, I stayed with my uncle.
First, I stayed with my
sister for a few days,
and then I moved
in with my uncle
because all of their
children were gone.
And they had a big house.
So I moved in there for
the first three months.
And then after I found work, I
moved out of there on my own.
I see.
In general, did people
want to learn about what
you had gone through?
No.
Nobody was really interested.
Nobody was interested.
In two ways, I think
it's a two-way street.
First we were not
reluctant to talk.
You mean you were reluctant.
Reluctant to talk.
You were reluctant to talk.
Reluctant to talk
with strangers.
Of course.
And the most talking came
between ourselves, all kinds
of things between ourselves.
You mean you with your sister?
What about these friends?
Between us.
Friends from home came
that you knew too.
Right, yes.
Fellow survivors.
Why did you decide
to leave Israel?
Well, it was Israel, I left
Israel because first of all,
I had no family there.
I see.
You had this sister
naturally there is this--
this tie.
And my sister somehow,
she says she felt--
She wanted somebody.
She wanted me to be.
I can understand.
So and I felt empty in Israel
at holidays and all that.
OK, I used to have
friends and all of that.
But still my sister is family.
Family is family, right.
Right.
When you came to Cleveland
then, did you join a synagogue?
Yes, I joined at the time the
Marmarosher Jewish Temple,
which was on Lancashire.
That was a Hungarian
congregation.
Yes, Hungarian congregation,
and till this--
Why did you join?
What, the temple?
Well, because I felt
I'm part of Jewish.
That's right.
Your religion meant something,
still meant something.
Was your rabbi helpful
or comforting in any way?
We didn't talk with the rabbi.
We didn't talk with
anybody on that.
All of them was a, so
to speak, we were we.
The rest of it is
an outside world.
In other words,
meant nothing to us.
How did you feel as a
Jew in the United States?
Well, the one thing that
I liked it, and I still do
is that first of all, that I'm
protected by the Constitution.
I can go where I want, and when
I want, and do what I want.
Which, of course,
to us and to me,
especially, I had the
same thing in Israel.
But Israel is Israel.
It's the Jewish state.
Here, it's not the Jewish state.
It's different compared
to what was there.
Besides, it's America.
Everybody has the same
rights, and the same thing,
as long as it's in the framework
of the law and order, which
is for everybody to obey.
And nobody's privileged to be
different than anybody else.
I liked it.
I loved it.
It's beautiful.
No problem about that.
Can you please tell me how your
Holocaust experiences affect
you now?
Yes.
They do affect me.
I see humanity and life from
a different perspective.
You see, from my perspective
America has developed today,
especially in the--
I don't know, if it's only
in the Jewish community
or is it Jewish, issues or
is it Jewish reflections,
or if it is human reflections.
I don't know.
I have never been
anything else but a Jew.
I understand.
So I look at it from the
Jewish point of view.
And it's not what you
know, it's who you know.
It not what you stand for
as a man, as a human being.
It's rather what you--
and not what you represent,
but rather what you possess.
So in other words,
it's a different thing.
Well, do you think that comes
from your Holocaust experience?
No, no, no, no.
This is what I'm asking you?
That's the way I'm looking
at from my point of view,
the way from my Holocaust
experiences, the way I see.
That you mean the way
you see people today.
Humanity.
I see.
Their values are very different.
Different in a way, in
the way they are dividing.
And something else, there's
a lot of people today.
Are you cynical?
No.
That's a fact.
Oh, OK.
That to me it's a fact.
That it's not.
To you or to another,
it's an outsider.
That's what I'm
trying to bring out
the insider and the outsider.
You see?
You hear a lot about
the Holocaust today.
And a lot has been written.
And probably a lot more will
be written, and a lot of more
will be discussed.
And there is no expert
on the Holocaust.
Because to understand
the Holocaust,
you've got to look at it only
from three point of views.
And the one point of
view is what kind of man
can do that kind of brutality,
or that kind of things
to another man.
And then what kind of humanity
has existed at that time that
permitted itself?
Permitted between themselves
something like this to happen.
And then you have to look at it
from the Jewish point of view.
It's not easy to say
and to point a finger.
But before you point the
finger, look at yourself
and say, what have
I not contributed?
What have I not done?
And I let myself to be put
in the position where I was.
So what kind of
Jewish leadership,
what kind of Jewish
existence did I
have as a Jew at
that particular time
that I permitted myself
in the framework of what
happened to be there?
Did you think you
could control it?
Yes, we could.
How could you have
controlled it?
Well, plain and simply, by if
we had known what's going on,
we could have not
gone, like resisted.
But you if you had known what
was going on, you said that--
If you had more information,
it would have been
a little bit more organized.
We could have had
the resistance.
There were pockets
of resistance.
The Warsaw ghetto
was resistance.
Of course.
And yes, the Germans
paid a price for it.
They didn't took it easy.
In Budapest, there
was resistance.
I remember being a part of a
group going out to the streets
and we observed,
and we saw Germans
that the youth, the
Hakenkreuz youth,
which the German Hakenkreuz
youth who call themselves.
We used to go over, I remember
it positively, and definitely,
and extremely well.
We run over to those kids, and
we said, hey, you're Jewish.
They said, what do
you mean you're a Jew.
I'm not Jewish.
I said you're a Jew.
We had the same Hakenkreuz on.
We spoke their language.
And we said you're Jewish.
And then we took them underneath
to show that they are not Jew.
They let their pants down and
prove that you're not Jewish.
And then we beat the hell
out of them right there.
There were incidents already
killed them right there.
So there was all kind
of way of resistance.
But when you see
in those frameworks
and the way things
have been, you see,
that's the way it happened.
How often do you talk
about the Holocaust?
Well, we mostly
between ourselves
we talk very often,
almost every time.
You have lots of friends.
With the friends, yes.
Survivors.
But it's always we
will remain no matter
what anybody says, no matter
how fancy he sees himself,
and nice words or
plain words, we will
remain on outside of humanity.
We can never be
part of the humanity
as in the way with
this experience.
There is always--
You think it's
affected your whole.
Absolutely.
And everybody, you think it's
affected the way everybody
looks at you.
No, no, no, no, no.
No, no, not in that sense.
And I'm talking all
of the survivors.
Yes.
They are all at the same.
No matter what they say,
one way or the other,
that's the way the feelings.
And that's the way--
You think it's affected your
whole social relationship
with everybody.
Absolutely.
We look at man, of our fellow
men from a different angle,
from a different point of
view, and from a different--
with all the knowledge.
So you think that survivors
are different from other Jews?
Absolutely.
How?
It's their own feeling.
It's there inside by paying a
commendous humanly impossible
to explain in words,
the price they paid
in order for their Jewishness.
So therefore, you look on it of
their being of this Jewishness.
Of course, whatever
experiences any of us
go through affect our
behavior and our thoughts.
I can understand
what you're saying.
OK, now you see, it affects if
somebody survives an accident,
a car accident.
Somebody survives an illness.
Sure, it affects their life.
Right.
It affects in different things
affect us in different ways.
That's true.
And this-- but when we have been
abused, for months and years,
in everyday life, and
in everyday happenings,
it's a story in itself.
And it's each one, even
individually locks his own,
so to speak lock, and
looks for his own key
to open up that particular.
Larry, do you think there are
any reasons for your survival?
Do you ever think about that?
Is there any reason
why you survived?
I don't know if the reason--
a reason is-- this is
a question beyond me.
Because they are factors
which are beyond my control
in order to be able--
You don't think
it was just luck?
I can speak only from
the human point of view.
No, I'm asking about your
point of view, from you.
That's what I mean.
Yeah.
From mine, as a human being,
from my own human being point
of view--
Right.
Going beyond the mysticism
and all of that, from my,
it was involved two
things, the will of power
to survive no matter what.
Age, I was young.
I could take the abuse.
I could stand it
and all of that.
And to cope with it.
To cope with the circumstances
and to cope with--
Your resourcefulness.
And that is the main
thing for the survival.
And then there is
an element of luck.
To be, so to speak, what we
say today in our modern terms,
of being at the right
place in the right time.
Right.
And that made a lot of to
do with many survivors.
Sure.
What thoughts do you
have now when you
remember what you went through?
Stupidity of humanity.
Do we ever going to learn?
There are so many wise men said
so many statements, so many
fancy words.
Like the guy who said, if you
don't learn from our mistakes,
we are bound to regret.
I forgot the name of the
philosopher who said that.
Now how many times have
you learned already
throughout history?
And how many times have people,
nations, and all regret?
Are we learning the consequences
from it, till this day?
Is man's inhumanity
towards man changed?
We know about it.
Right, right, right.
And in fact, with
all those development
of new weapons and new
stuff, more destructive,
more terrible, with
more pain and tears
to inflict on each other.
And start to find ways
to co-exist and to exist
and to better for ourselves.
Larry, do you think
that survivors
have a message that
others need to understand?
The survivors have
more than a message.
And I'm coming to
conclusion to believe
that a problem is because it's
looked on us like a message.
And it's more than a message.
It's not a message.
It's when I said before in the
[? readings. ?] You remember?
On what kind of
humanity existed.
The same humanity exists
today with a little bit
more knowledge, and with a
little bit more know-how.
But we don't have the power more
than to bring it across to you
and telling you of
what you, humanity, are
capable in doing to yourself.
And what good is it?
We are bringing it across.
We are trying to tell you.
Nobody came down
from outer space
and did to us what
has been done.
Only human beings from
here who arrived here
in the same way we did,
who live in the same way.
As here as Jews,
as Jewish people,
for generations we have been
telling the non-Jewish world,
look.
When we are sick, we need
a doctor and medicine.
When we are hungry,
we need food.
When we are cold, we need
clothing and shelter.
We have beautiful
looking women, so do you.
We have great athletes.
So do you.
We have wise men.
We have stupid men.
So do you.
So we are not
differently than you are.
Yet, at every so
often, we are getting
trodden down and
down to us what has
been done throughout history.
But it's repeating itself.
Every time, every so
often, and humanity
does not want to accept.
Or they do not want to listen.
Well, in your opinion, what
would be an appropriate way
to commemorate the
memory of those
who lost their lives
during the Holocaust years?
The best way to commemorate
is first of all,
let's not make out
of it a Jewish issue.
We were Jews, the victims.
Let's make it a human issue.
Well, there were
many more than Jews
who died during the
Holocaust years, right?
Right.
This is what you're telling me.
Exactly right,
But the difference
between the two of them is this.
If you were Polish, French,
Czech, or whatever nationality,
you lived in your own country.
If you obey the
rules and the laws
of the occupational
force, most of the time
they didn't bother you.
You could have a
chance to survive.
But with us, we didn't
have this chance.
We were Jews.
And as a Jew, you were
condemned automatically,
no matter what your beliefs are,
and in what country you live.
You were automatically
condemned.
That makes the difference.
That's number one.
And number two, it was a
Christian world around us
what did happen.
And let Christianity understand
that their indifference is not
the answer.
There were many Christian
leaders who stood up,
no question on that.
But they were in a minority.
And their voice wasn't heard.
They were not even
permitted to listen.
So countries where freedom of
speech and freedom of action
in everything is
free and possible,
they should stand
up and be heard.
And this is where
we survivors have
to bring across the message.
To understand what
it can be done.
I heard today from Jews,
my own Jewish people,
saying that a religious
Jew wouldn't touch it
with a 10 foot pole.
It's not right.
I didn't understand.
A Jew, religious Jews don't want
to talk about the Holocaust.
Why?
Because their belief is
that it was God's doing.
What God had to do with it?
I don't buy that.
God didn't create the Holocaust.
It was man's
inhumanity towards man.
It wasn't God.
There are Christians I heard
many times Christianity saying,
learn to forgive and to forget.
I cannot forget.
Of course not.
And to forgive, it's not a
question of me, will I forgive,
of me Larry Hersh, as a
Jew and as a survivor.
The question is,
would Jesus the Jew
forgive them for their silence?
It's not me.
What good is the
entire Christianity?
As when the chips are down
and when his teachings count,
they're not there.
I have one, just one
further question, Larry.
In what ways can those of
us who are not survivors
relate to those of
you who went through
these terrible experiences?
Do you expect is there anything
that we, as caring and humane
people, can do to relate to
you and your experiences?
Yes.
The only way a
relationship can be
is that you understand
what we went through,
show that you have their
human, show understanding
because remember, the majority
of us I happen to be lucky
that I have a sister.
But the majority without--
Without anyone.
--anybody or anything.
Be honest and let's
look the facts.
How many people do
you know that have
invited a survivor just to
come over and say, hey hello.
Come over on a holiday,
on a Jewish holiday.
Let's spend a Pesach
one evening with us,
spend a holiday with us.
How many families
like this do you know?
I don't.
And I have never heard of it.
The bridges between the Jewish
communities and the survivors,
and for this matter
even with humanity,
has never been crossed.
Now, it's obvious what happened.
It happened to him.
He is from somewhere else.
And this is still this day.
Well, your story has
been fascinating.
And we much, much appreciate
your telling it to us.
More than welcome.
I just--
Thank you.
Thank you so very, very much.
I just hope that
what I have told
the future generations
will be able to draw
the consequences from it, and
understand that there is only
like we Jews say, there's one
God, and there's one humanity.
And that's--
That's the lesson to be learned.
And that's the must.
And if somebody gets--
if any man of any religion,
of any race, or of any color
is getting depressed or
is suffering depression
for no other reason than
just for being what he is,
humanity must stand
up and speak up.
And this is the only way we
ever survive as a humanity.
OK.
Again, many, many thanks.
You're more than welcome.
It's a beautiful
contribution to our archives.
Thank you very much.